Guide to the Marion Belanger Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marion Belanger photographs
1998-2014
WA Photos Folio 153
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4
(2 boxes)
Photographs created by Marion Belanger that document sites and activities in Hawaii, Utah, and Yellowstone National Park in Wyoming. Images captured 1998-2003, and printed 1998-2014. Photographs of Hawaii created in 1999 include sites on Hawaii Island and Maui, including Haleakala National Park and Hawaii Volcanoes National Park. Photographs of Utah created in 2003 include documentation of fowling for swan at the Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge as well as views of Great Salt Lake and of the Spiral Jetty, an earthwork sculpture built on the northeastern shore of the Great Salt Lake near Rozel Point in April 1970 by sculptor Robert Smithson. Photographs of sites in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, created in 1998 include views of Mammoth Hot Springs and Old Faithful.
Belanger, Marion, 1957-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Marion Belanger on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2014.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Hawaii, 1999-2014. II. Utah, 2003-2014. III. Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, 1998-2014.
Marion Belanger (born 1957)
Marion Belanger, Yale MFA 1990, is a photographer. Her work focuses on the cultural landscape, particularly where geology and the built environment intersect.
Scope and Contents
Photographs created by Marion Belanger that document sites and activities in Hawaii, Utah, and Yellowstone National Park in Wyoming. Images captured, 1998-2003, and printed 1998-2014. Photographs of Hawaii created in 1999 include sites on Hawaii Island and Maui, including Haleakala National Park and Hawaii Volcanoes National Park. Photographs of Utah created in 2003 include documentation of fowling for swan at the Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge as well as views of Great Salt Lake and of the Spiral Jetty, an earthwork sculpture built on the northeastern shore of the Great Salt Lake near Rozel Point in April 1970 by sculptor Robert Smithson. Photographs of sites in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, created in 1998 include views of Mammoth Hot Springs and Old Faithful.
Conditions Governing Access
The Marion Belanger Photographs are the physical property of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors or their legal heirs and assigns. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Smithson, Robert. Spiral Jetty -- Pictorial works; Fowling -- Utah -- Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge -- Pictorial works; National parks and reserves -- Hawaii -- Pictorial works; National parks and reserves -- Wyoming -- Pictorial works; Swans -- Utah -- Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge -- Pictorial works; Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge (Utah) -- Pictorial works; Great Salt Lake (Utah) -- Pictorial works; Haleakala National Park (Hawaii) -- Pictorial works; Hawaii -- Pictorial works; Hawaii Island (Hawaii) -- Pictorial works; Hawaii Volcanoes National Park (Hawaii) -- Pictorial works; Mammoth Hot Springs (Wyo.) -- Pictorial works; Maui (Hawaii) -- Pictorial works; Old Faithful Geyser (Wyo.) -- Pictorial works; Wyoming -- Pictorial works; Yellowstone National Park -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Photographic prints; Photographs; Belanger, Marion, 1957-; Smithson, Robert
- Hawaii, 1999–2014
  Scope and Contents
  Views of sites in Hawaii created in 1999 and printed in 1999 and 2014 as selenium toned black-and-white gelatin silver prints, 16 x 20 inches (40.64 x 50.8 centimeters). This component includes sites on Hawaii Island and Maui, including Haleakala National Park and Hawaii Volcanoes National Park. The prints comprise an edition numbered one of fifteen except where an artist's proof is noted in this guide.
  Arrangement
  Organized under two headings for Hawaii Island and Maui.
  - Hawaii Island
    - Green Sand Beach, Hawaii, image created and printed in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      Site also known as Mahana Beach and Papakōlea Beach
    - Lava Enveloped Road, Volcanoes National Park, Hawaii, image created and printed in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - Lava Over Road, Volcanoes National Park, Hawaii, printed in 2014; image created in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
  - Maui
    - Haleakala National Park, Maui, image created and printed in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
      Parenthetically referred to Belanger as "Path"
    - Rainbow, Haleakala National Park, Maui, image created and printed in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
    - Volcanic Stones, Haleakala, Maui, image created and printed in 1999 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 6)
      Artist's proof
- Utah, 2003–2014
  Photographs of Utah made in 2003 of activities and sites at the Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge and of Great Salt Lake and its vicinity.
  - Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge, 2003
    Views that document fowling for swan at the Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge created in 2003 and printed in 2014 as color inkjet prints using pigmented ink on Hahnemuhle Photo Rag Pearl Paper, 17 x 22 inches (43.18 x 55.88 centimeters). The prints comprise a library edition numbered one of four.
    - Bear River Migratory Bird Refuge, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    - Hunter in Camouflage, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 8)
    - Hunter with Cellphone and Duck, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 9)
    - Hunter with Swan, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 10)
    - Hunter with Yellow Glasses, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 11)
    - Hunter, Waiting, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 12)
    - Juvenile Swan, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 13)
    - Three Hunters with Car, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 14)
    - Three Hunters with Swans, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 15)
    - Three Hunters, Standing, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 16)
    - Wetlands with Birds, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 17)
    - Wetlands, #2, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 18)
  - Great Salt Lake
    Views of Great Salt Lake, Utah, and of the Spiral Jetty, an earthwork sculpture built on the northeastern shore of the Great Salt Lake near Rozel Point in April 1970 by sculptor Robert Smithson (1938-1973), which is a 1,500-foot-long (460 meters), 15-foot-wide (4.6 meters) counterclockwise coil jutting into the water from the lakeshore. The images were created in 2003 and printed in 2014 that comprise selenium toned black-and-white gelatin silver prints, 16 x 20 inches (40.64 x 50.8 centimeters) and color inkjet prints using pigmented ink on Hahnemuhle Photo Rag Pearl Paper, 17 x 22 inches (43.18 x 55.88 centimeters). The black-and-white prints comprise an edition numbered one of fifteen. The color inkjet prints comprise a library edition numbered one of four.
    Organized under two headings for Black-and-white Gelatin Silver Prints and Color Inkjet Prints
    - Black-and-white Gelatin Silver Prints
      - Spiral Jetty, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
      - Trailer, Spiral Jetty Shore, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
      - Vehicles, Spiral Jetty Shore, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 21)
    - Color Inkjet Prints
      - Dry Lake Bed, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
      - Fog, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
      - Fog, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 24)
      - Rusted Parts, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)
      - Spiral Jetty from Shore, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 26)
      - Spiral Jetty with People, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 27)
      - Spiral Jetty, Aerial, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 28)
      - Trailer near Spiral Jetty, printed in 2014; image created in 2003 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 29)
- Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, 1998–2014
  Views of sites in Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming, including Mammoth Hot Springs and Old Faithful, were created in 1998 and printed in 1998 and 2014 as selenium toned black-and-white gelatin silver prints, 16 x 20 inches (40.64 x 50.8 centimeters). The prints comprise portions of editions numbered one and two of fifteen as well as artist's proofs and prints with no designated edition.
  - After the Fire, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 30)
  - Animal Bones, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 31)
  - Fumerole, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 32)
    Print numbered 2 of 15
  - Geyser Field, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 33)
  - Hot Spring with Steam, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 34)
  - Lava Field, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 35)
  - Mammoth Hot Springs, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 36)
  - Old Faithful, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 37)
  - Old Faithful, printed in 2014; image created in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 38)
    Print numbered 1 of 15
  - Plume, Old Faithful, image created and printed in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - Thermal Ground, printed in 2014; image created in 1998 (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 40)